<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meta | Welcome to My Nerditorium]]></title>
  <link href="http://nerditorium.danielauger.com/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nerditorium.danielauger.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-24T09:17:56-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://nerditorium.danielauger.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daniel Auger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up an Existing Octopress Blog on a New Computer]]></title>
    <link href="http://nerditorium.danielauger.com/blog/2013/06/22/setting-up-an-existing-octopress-blog-on-a-new-computer/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T12:52:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://nerditorium.danielauger.com/blog/2013/06/22/setting-up-an-existing-octopress-blog-on-a-new-computer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This information comes from a <a href="http://code.dblock.org/octopress-setting-up-a-blog-and-contributing-to-an-existing-one">post</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/dblockdotorg">@dblockdotorg</a> which was down today while I was trying to set my blog up on a fresh OS install. Therefore, I'm mirroring that content here in case it is unavailable in the future.</p>

<pre><code>$ git clone git@github.com:username/username.github.com.git
$ cd username.github.com
$ git checkout source
$ mkdir _deploy
$ cd _deploy
$ git init
$ git remote add origin git@github.com:username/username.github.com.git
$ git pull origin master
$ cd ..
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress: Banishing a Category to Its Own Page]]></title>
    <link href="http://nerditorium.danielauger.com/blog/2013/03/03/octopress-banishing-a-category-to-its-own-page/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-03T18:11:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://nerditorium.danielauger.com/blog/2013/03/03/octopress-banishing-a-category-to-its-own-page</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Because this blog is made of up <a href="/blog/categories/links">link posts</a> and original content posts, I wanted to make two customizations to Octopress to keep original content from getting lost under the volume of link posts.<!-- more --> The modifications I wanted to make were:</p>

<ol>
<li>Hide all link posts from the index page.</li>
<li>Create a page just for link posts and provide navigation to it via the nav bar.</li>
</ol>


<p>I wasn't sure where to start because I am new to Octopress. My google-fu was questionable due to my lack of understanding Octopress' terminology.</p>

<h2>Hiding Link Posts from the Index Page</h2>

<p>Out of the two things I wanted to do, this was the easiest to find help with. I found this post about <a href="http://arshad.github.com/blog/2012/05/10/recipe-hiding-posts-from-the-octopress-front-page/">hiding posts from the octopress front page</a> almost right away.</p>

<p>The TLDR version of that post is: you need to assign a category to the posts you want to hide and then alter the pagination plugin to exclude that category.</p>

<h2>Creating a Page Just for the Hidden Category and Providing a Nav Link to It</h2>

<p>This one tripped me up for a bit. I quickly went down a black hole searching for things like "octopress create category page".</p>

<p>I couldn't find quite what I was looking for so I starting searching for other Octopress based blogs to see if anyone had done such a thing. After I came across <a href="http://time.to.pullthepl.ug/blog/archives/">this</a> blog, the answer was obvious. Octopress already creates category specific pages. In order to provide a nav link to the category, I simply needed to edit the _source/custom/navigation.html file like so:<br/>
```html</p>

<ul class="main-navigation">
  <!-- other nav links -->
  <li><a href="/blog/categories/links">10,000 Links</a></li>
  <!-- other nav links -->
</ul>


<p>```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
